A Guide to the Papers of The Albemarle County, Virginia Chapter of the United World Federalists
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Albemarle County, Virginia Chapter of the United World Federalists 1946-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
This collection consists of approximately 1,300 items (15 linear shelf feet, 3 Hollinger boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The United World Federalist papers were a gift of Charles E. Moran, August 1977, and bear no restriction
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of the Albemarle County, Virginia Chapter of the United World Federalists consist of approximately 1,300 items, ca. 1946-1954. The U.W.F. was an organization which worked toward the strengthening of the United Nations into a limite world government. The group believed that peace was "not merely the absence of war, but the presence of justice, law, and order; in short of government and the institutions of government." They felt that world peace could be created and maintained only under a world law strong enough to prevent armed conflict among nations. as a result, they endorsed the efforts of teh United nations to bring about a world community favorable to peace. The U.W.F. organized after World War II partly as a positive response to the formation of the U.N. and partly as a reaction against the use of the atomic bomb and development of nuclear weapons. The collection consists chiefly of printed materials on this and related issues. In addition, the papers include by-laws, minutes, financial records, correspondence, newsclippings and miscellaneous materials of the Albemarle County chapter together with national newsletters and periodicals. Charles E. Moran served as chairman of the local chapter from October 1949 until December 1950 when he resigned his post over an issue which seems to have divided the ranks of the U.W.F. The issue involved the state of emergency preceding the Korean War. Moran and others opposed U.S. preparedness for war as incongruent with the philosophy of the U.W.F.
Organization
The collection consists of three series: Correspondence, Organizational Papers, and Printed Matter. Materials are arranged chronologically within each series.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence of United World Federalists
  - Correspondence of the Albemarle United World Federalists 1946 Nov-1947 Jun (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Congress and State Dept ca. 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of the Albemarle United World Federalists 1947 July-1951 Nov; 1958 Jan 7, n.d., 9 folders (Box 1)
- Series II:Organizational Papers of the United World Federalists
  - By-Laws, Statement of Purpose & List of Branches of the Albemarle Chapter ca. 1946-1954 (Box 1)
  - General Policies 1947-1951, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the Albemarle Chapter 1946-1950 (Box 2)
  - Minutes of the Albemarle Chapter - Executive Council & Miscellaneous 1947-1949 (Box 2)
- Series III: Financial Records of the Albemarle County United World Federalists (Box 2)
  - Cancelled Checks, Stubs, and Bank Statements 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Deposit slips, & membership dues receipts 1948-1951 (Box 2)
  - Financial correspondence, Budget information, and miscellaneous receipts ca. 1947-1954 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers of the Albemarle United World Federalists ca. 1947-1954 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters - Albemarle United World Federalists 1947-1950, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Publications of United World Federalists ca. 1947-1954 (Box 2)
  - Copies of the U.N. Charter & related legislation ca. 1947-1954 (Box 2)
  - Newsclippings ca. 1947-1954 (Box 3)
  - Business Forms ca. 1947-1954 (Box 3)
  - Public Information ca. 1947-1954, 6 folders (Box 3)